================================================================================
EXTRACTING VIMSHOTTARI DASHA CALCULATION METHOD
From: Robert Svoboda - Light on Life
================================================================================

================================================================================
PAGE 307
================================================================================
the strength and position of the yogas. The less such a yoga is 
interfered with by the impact of other grahas, particularly malefics, 
the more the native will experience its energies. A Ruchaka Yoga, 
for example, is one thing when Mars is aspected by its friend 
Jupiter alone, and quite another when it is aspected by its enemy 
Saturn, and is conjoined with Rahu. 
Note that the indications for these yogas are mainly the significa- 
tions for the grahas involved, because a Pancha Mahapurusha 
Yoga allows a graha to express its inherent nature freely and 
strongly. The description of Ruchaka Yoga is clearly a glorified 
listing of the astrological attributes of Mars. Mantreshwara might 
as well have gone on to say that someone with Ruchaka Yoga 
will be fond of confrontations, will be a 'victory-at-any-cost' com- 
petitor, may be accident-prone, will serve in executive and inde- 
pendent positions, may be a crusader for various causes, may have 
powerful younger siblings, may be athletic, may be a lawyer, and 
SO on. 
Many people with strong Ruchaka Yogas do end up becoming 
lawyers, but this potential will be actualized only in those horoscopes 
i.. which the fourth house of education (because law requires formal 
education) and Jupiter (because law requires good judgement) are 
both strong. Similarly, a person with an unblemished Ruchaka 
Yoga may become an athlete if the first house is very strong, 
because athletes require strong bodies. 
One way to gauge the magnitude of a Pancha Mahapurusha Yoga 
is to see whether or not it recurs from all three lagnas (the 
ascendant, the Chandra Lagna and the Surya Lagna), which is a sort 
of confluence. That yoga which does so is very strong, all other 
factors remaining equal. A yoga which recurs from two lagnas is 
better than average, while a yoga which can be counted only from 
the ascendant is only average. In Chart 2 (see p. 41 8) a Hamsa Yoga 
exists in the fourth house of the lagna, the fourth house of the 
Surya Lagna, and the seventh house of the Chandra Lagna. As we 
might expect, this Hamsa Yoga has created in the person concerned 
many Jupiterian qualities. Because this yoga is specific to the bhavas 
that Jupiter owns, we may conclude that this person will own 
expensive or valuable vehicles and houses (fourth house) and will 


================================================================================
PAGE 308
================================================================================
have a noble and educated spouse (seventh house) - which, in fact, 
he does. 
The classical texts mention other indications for these yogas 
which cannot be derived as easily as we have derived these general 
conclusions. For example, Brihaf Parashara Hora says that a person 
with Hamsa Yoga will be fond of playing games and of watery 
places. Chart 2's owner does indeed live on a property with a pond, 
and very much enjoys amusements. The same text also states that 
such an individual will have full cheeks and a round forehead, two 
characteristics which this person does possess. 
Simply because a graha occupies its own or its exaltation constella- 
tion does not create a Pancha Mahapurusha Yoga. Venus, which 
occupies Libra in Chart 2, is conjoined with the benefic Mercury. 
This is an auspicious placement, but it is no Malavya Yoga because 
it sits in the second house, which is neither a kendra nor a kona. 
Likewise, in Chart I (see p. 41)) Jupiter is exalted but is in the 
second house, so that no Hamsa Yoga is formed. Anyway, this 
Jupiter is combust and is conjoined with Rahu, which spoils many 
of its indications. rs does occupy Aries, its own constellation, 
but being in the eleve ? th house it does not form Ruchaka Yoga. It 
is, however, likely to give good results, since Mars is aspected here 
only by the benefic waxing Moon. 
An exalted planet which occupies a kendra or kona will create a 
Pancha Mahapurusha Yoga only if its dispositor is strong. When a 
graha occupies its own house, it serves as its own dispositor, and is 
by definition strong in both body and soul. An exalted graha whose 
dispositor is afflicted by malefics, is combust or debilitated is highly 
unlikely to be able to deliver the promised goods for, though its 
body (deha) is powerful, its soul (@a) is feeble. 
THE DHARMA KARMA ADHIPATI YOGAS 
Another class of yogas for which jyotishis always look are the 
Dharma Karma Adh$ati Yogas, the 'Combinations of the Lords of 
Fortune and Action'. This yoga is formed when the lords of a 
dharma house (a kona) and a karma house (a kendra) combine in a 


================================================================================
PAGE 309
================================================================================
horoscope, either by aspect or by association. 'Karma' means action, 
and 'dharma' indicates fortune, in the sense that those people who 
dedicatedly follow their own individual dharmas find that luck 
begins to follow them around. Real success in life appears whenever 
there is a felicitous conjunction of effort with luck. Enterprise alone 
is no guarantee of achievement, nor can chance alone be relied 
upon; but when both combine, the whole truly becomes greater 
than the sum of its parts. Whenever Napoleon was considering 
elevating one of his generals to the rank of marshal, his final 
question, after hearing a litany of the man's achievements and 
qualifications, would reportedly be: 'Yes, but is he lucky?' 
Dharma Karma Adhipati Yogas are examples of Raja Yogas, 
combinations which promise success, wealth, influence and celebrity. 
A strong Dharma Karma Adhipati Yoga enables a person to rise to 
a position of great prominence in society. Although, technically 
speaking, a Raja Yoga is a combination for political success (a raja 
is a ruler), over the years it has come to promise success, wealth, 
influence and/or celebrity. While in the old days the king had the 
power to support and influence all others, today non-political 
people like writers, actors, musicians and media moguls are often 
more influential, wealthy and famous than most of our rulers. 
The source of good fortune is the Law of Karma: The total of 
your past karmas determines what sort of assistance the world will 
give you. The kendras represent, in a certain sense, your present 
actions, your Kriyamana and Agama Karmas, while the konas 
indicate the overall positivity or negativity of your past actions, 
your Prarabdha and Sanchita Karmas. Parashara explains (Brihat 
Parashara Hora 41:28) that the kendras are bhavas of Vishnu, the 
Surmounter of Difficulties, while the konas are bhavas of Lakshmi, 
His wife, the Goddess of Prosperity. The lagna is particularly 
important because it is simultaneously a kona and a kendra. When- 
ever the lord of a kendra (the husband) and the lord of a kona (his 
wife) unite, opportunity combines with real fortune to create endur- 
ing prosperity: a Raja Yoga. 
Here is another way to look at this combination: The kendra 
houses are sometimes called houses of environment (your objective 
surroundings) and the trinal houses, houses of merit (your subjective 


================================================================================
PAGE 310
================================================================================
attitudes). When the ohctive and subjective factors in a ho~oscope 
combine harmoniously, they create by their confluence a powerful 
current, for then conscious (subjective) attitudes become aligned 
with the unconscious (objective) influences. If subjectively you 
happen to be academically gifted and inclined to study, and objec- 
tively you happen to live a stone's throw from Harvard Yard, then 
y~ili! environment and merit have combined, and success becomes 
almost inevitable. 
A Dharma Karma Adhipati Yoga which involves either the lords 
of the ninth and tenth houses or the lords of the fourth and fifth 
houses is particularly valuable. The combination of the ninth and 
tenth lords is the strongest Dharma Karma Adhipati Yoga, for the 
ninth is the strongest of the konas and the tenth the strongest of the 
kendras. Although a Dharma Karma Adhipati Yoga is defined as a 
combination by association or mutual aspect between a kona lord 
and a kendra lord, it is also said to be formed when: (a) the lord of 
the ninth house occupies the ninth house and the tenth lord occupies 
the tenth house, or when the fourth lord occupies the fourth and the 
fifth lord tenants the fifth. (In these cases, two Pancha Mahapurusha 
Yogas are often formed.) (b) the lord of the ninth occupies the 
tenth and the tenth lord dwells in the ninth, or the fourth lord 
appears in the fifth and the fifth lord resides in the fourth. (This is a 
type of Parzuartana Yoga see below.) 
In certain lagnas a single graha owns both a kendra and a kona. 
Such a planet becomes a Raja Yoga Karaka ('Raja Yoga Significator'), 
a single-graha Dharma Karma Adhipati Yoga which, if well placed 
in the horoscope, will produce very desirable results. Listed below 
are the planets which can act as Raja Yoga Karakas, and the lagnas 
for which they so act. Note that each of the Raja Yoga Karakas is a 
friend to the lord of the lagna in which they own the kendra and the 
kona: 
For Taurus lagna: Saturn (lord of houses 9 & 10) 
For Cancer lagna: Mars (lord of houses 5 & lo) 
For Leo lagna: Mars (lord of houses 4 & 9) 
For Libra lagna: Saturn (lord of houses 4 & I) 
For Capricorn lagna: Venus (lord of houses 5 & I o) 
For Aquarius lagna: Venus (lord of houses 4 & 9) 


================================================================================
PAGE 311
================================================================================
288 LIGHT ON LIFE 
Although Raja Yoga Karakas when well placed can singly create 
Raja Yoga, they should ideally be supported by benefics or by the 
rulers of beneficial houses. This is particularly true for Cancer 
lagna, because Mars, the Raja Yoga Karaka, is debilitated in the 
first house. It is sometimes said that Mars forms Raja Yoga for a 
Cancer ascendant only when it is supported by benefics. 
Saturn acts as Raja Yoga Karaka for the ascendants of Venus, 
and Venus returns the favor for Saturn. Symmetry suggests that the 
Moon and Sun, lords of Cancer and Leo respectively, should, when 
conjoined, form a Raja Yoga for the two ascendants of Mars (Aries, 
in which the luminaries own houses 4 and r, and Scorpio, in which 
they rule 9 and 10). Because whenever the Sun and Moon occupy 
the same house the Moon's inherent light is exceedingly dim, the 
Raja Yoga formed when the Sun and Moon aspect one another (as 
they do when the Moon is full or near full) is much stronger than 
is the yoga formed when they conjoin, at the time of the new 
Moon. 
Like any other beneficial yoga, a Raja Yoga gives good results 
when it appears in a good house and is without affliction. Consider 
a Saturn at z9' in the first house of a Libra ascendant in the 
horoscope of a person about to enter a period where Saturn will be 
very influential in her life. For Saturn as the Raja Yoga Karaka to 
be exalted in Libra is very desirable, for it also creates a Shasha 
Yoga in the first house, and Saturn is a friend of Venus, the lord of 
the lagna. But - because Saturn occupies its Mrita Avastha there 
may be danger to health (since Saturn = ill health and the first 
house = the body), danger of bankruptcy (because Saturn is the 
natural house significator of the three evil trik houses; this is one 
reason why Saturn is the significator of misery) and danger to 
profession (because Saturn aspects the tenth house as a significator 
of the tenth house). 
In Chart 2 (see p. 418) the lords of the ninth and tenth houses 
(Mercury and Venus) both occupy the second house, and the lords 
of the fourth and fifth houses (Jupiter and Saturn) tenant the fourth 
house. The grahas involved are all strong, being in their own, in 
friendly or at the very least in neutral rashis, and are simultaneously 
in good houses (that is, the non-dussthanas). The two pairs of 


================================================================================
PAGE 312
================================================================================
planets involved - Mercury/Venus and JupiterISaturn - are not 
inimical to each other, nor are they enemies of the lord of the lagna. 
These yogas will therefore strongly influence those areas of life 
indicated by the houses in which they occur; and we have already 
seen that this man is a millionaire (second house) and enjoys 
good, profitable property (fourth house). After handling many birth 
charts you will begin to realize how unusual it is to find two such 
strong Dharma Karma Adhipati Yogas in one and the same 
horoscope. 
Experience will also teach you that these and other yogas occur 
in horoscopes with some frequency but with very different strengths. 
Be mindful of Mantreshwara's axiom that the results of good yogas 
become certain when the grahas involved are strong and when there 
is a confluence of good influences to the participant planets. Contrast 
now the condition of the combination of the lords of the fourth and 
fifth houses in Chart 2 with the same combination in Chart I. In 
Chart I, the two planets involved (Mercury and Venus) sit together 
in the third house, a dussthana; Venus is in the constellation of its 
enemy; and both Mercury and Venus are aspected by the malefic 
Saturn, who is also acting as eighth lord. 
Saturn as the fifth lord joins with Jupiter in Chart 2 to form the 
yoga, so we cannot say that the yoga there is marred by the malefic 
Saturn. There is a drawback in Chart 2 in the aspect of the malefic 
Mars, who also owns the eighth house, on the Jupiter-Saturn 
combination, but this, as your experience will eventually enable you 
to conclude, is a minor blemish on an otherwise strong yoga. Some 
slight imperfection always occurs, alas, in even the best of horo- 
scopes; such is the nature of embodied life. 
We must also examine a Dharma Karma Adhipati Yoga from the 
Moon and Sun Lagnas. Recall the five human bodies, the annamayako- 
sha (physical body), pranamayakosha (etheric body), manomayakosha 
(subtle body), uijnanamqakosha (causal body) and anandamayakosha 
(greater causal body). The ascendant (Birth Lagna) represents the 
physical body, the Moon Lagna the subtle body (and hence desire 
manifestation), and the Sun Lagna the causal body (and hence 
thought manifestation). Congruence of thoughts and desires with 
actions, which leads to integrated activity, occurs when yogas and 


================================================================================
PAGE 313
================================================================================
planetary combinations recur from all three lagnas; this is yet 
another form of confluence. 
In Chart 2 the many Raja Yogas all recur from the Sun Lagna. 
Moreover, when we count from the Moon we see that the fourth 
and fifth house lords are conjoined in the fifth house, that the ninth 
and tenth house lords are conjoined in the seventh house, and that 
all the same grahas that were involved in the yogas in the other two 
lagnas (namely, Mercury-Venus and Jupiter-Saturn) are involved 
here. This is a clear case of confluence. Contrast this situation with 
that in Chart I where the already feeble yoga counted from the 
lagna (the fourth and fifth lords combined in the third house) 
does not recur from the other lagnas. Such a yoga is unlikely to 
yield anywhere near the bounty which those yogas in Chart 2 will 
afford. 
OTHER GRAHA YOGAS 
A partial list of yogas commonly cited in various Jyotish texts 
appears below. Specific meanings are provided for some; the reader 
should analyze the others with the help of the basic interpretive 
method explained in the last chapter. Always blend together the 
significations of the grahas, rashis and bhavas to arrive at an 
interpretation. Examples of ways in which to interpret yogas can be 
found in Chapter Twelve. One general rule: The more yogas in which a 
graha participates, the greater its importance. 
A D H I YOGA : Benefics occupying simdtaneous~ the sixth, the seventh 
and the eighth houses, counted from either the Moon or the ascendant. In 
Adhi Yoga benefics in the sixth and eighth houses flank the seventh 
house, which strengthens that house, and any planet therein. The 
aspect on the first house of such a strengthened benefic in the 
seventh house will then produce most favorable effects. This yoga 
is particularly good for raising one to a position of leadership (adhi 
means 'to add, to receive'). 
AMALA YOGA: An unaffEicted benefic occupying the tenth home from the 
Moon or the Lagna (amala means 'stainless'). Planets in the tenth 


================================================================================
PAGE 314
================================================================================
house from the lagna, the zenith of the horoscope, shine there 
brilliantly. Amala Yoga tends to make the native's actions (tenth 
house) stainless (virtuous, pious, etc.). Such a person will be revered 
by the sovereign, which is one way in which a benefic in the tenth 
house enhances tenth-house meanings. 
AS HUB HA MA LA YOGA: When all the benefic grahas tenant homes six, 
eight and twelve. This very undesirable combination (Ashubha Mala 
means 'the necklace of inauspiciousness') indicates great difficulties 
in life, just as the albatross around the neck of the Ancient Mariner 
betokened his ruination. If there are benefics in houses six and eight 
alone, the beneficial influence is reduced somewhat, but is not 
canceled. That situation is therefore also a sort of Adhi Yoga 
(benefics in the sixth, seventh and eighth houses) and not an 
ex4rnple of Ashubha Mala Yoga. Ashubha Mala Yoga occurs onh 
when all benefics lie in the sixth house alone, in the eighth house 
alone, in the sixth and twelfth houses only, or in the eighth and 
twelfth houses only. In these cases all the power of the benefics is 
completely eclipsed, robbing the native of all good influences. 
BUDHADITYA YOGA: When the St/n and Mercur occupy the same 
constellation. This famous yoga, which is prevalent (because Mercury 
can never be more than one rashi away from the Sun), confuses 
many who try to interpret it. While a Budhaditya Yoga is supposed 
to illumine one's intellect, every jyotishi finds it in the horoscopes 
of dullards and geniuses alike. Some people attempt to use this fact 
to undermine the theory of combustion, since a combust Mercury 
should (if combust planets are weak) give such natives uniformly 
weak intellects. But, as we noted in the previous chapter, an 
individual's inner qualities such as intellect are not necessarily 
impaired when their significators are combust. When intelligence is 
impaired in someone who has a Budhaditya Yoga, it is often due to 
other influences. 
However, for a Budhaditya Yoga to be really effective in a 
horoscope it must above all be somehow configured with either the 
ascendant (the chief indicator of the individual) or the fifth house 
(intellect), with the first house being preferred. When this is so, the 
following criteria must then be met: (a) If either the Sun or Mercury 


================================================================================
PAGE 315
================================================================================
owns either the first or the fifth houses, the yoga must appear in a 
good house. (b) If neither graha owns either house, the yoga must 
occur in either the ascendant, the seventh house (from which it 
aspects the ascendant), the fifth house or the eleventh house (from 
which it aspects the fifth). (c) Under all circumstances the grahas 
should be strong and not otherwise afflicted, and the first and fifth 
houses must be strong. 
CHANDRA MANGALA YOGA: When the Moon and Mars occupy the same 
constellation. By extension (though this is not a classical precept), the 
Yoga is also formed when Moon and Mars mutually aspect. If the 
Yoga happens in good houses, particularly the elevated houses of 
the horoscope (nine, ten, eleven), and the Moon is bright and 
powerful, this Yoga can contribute considerably to the native's 
financial status, more especially if it is a night birth. 
In a male horoscope Chandra Mangala Yoga also connotes gains 
through women, or through such industries as hospitality (hotels, 
food, and the like) and the personal beautification industry (exercise, 
dieting, hairdressing, and so on). If the Yoga is afflicted (if it occurs 
in houses six, eight or twelve, is aspected by malefics and/or there is 
no aspect of benefics), it may mean exploitation of wornen. 
DUR YOGA: When the trik lords are strongly positioned in kendras or 
konas, and the lords of houses one, four, nine and ten are weak or combust 
and occupy the trik houses. This yoga (mentioned in Phaladipika 6:70) 
should not be confused with the yoga of the same name included in 
the group of twenty-four Yogas below. The results, while similar, 
are more pervasive, rendering difficult the entire horoscope instead 
of only the tenth house. If Dur (difficult) Yoga is reversed (with the 
trik lords weak or combust and the lords of houses one, four, nine 
and ten strong in kendras or konas), the native will be wealthy, 
happy, virtuous and powerful. 
Whole systems of interpretation have been built on the principle 
which lies at Dur Yoga's root: the lords of dussthanas cause 
difficulties when they are strong and occupy non-dussthanas, while 
the lords of good houses cause good results when in kendras and 
konas. When the lord of a dussthana is weak, it is no longer capable 
of giving in plenty the evil results which it otherwise promises, any 


================================================================================
PAGE 316
================================================================================
more than the lords of good houses can give their promised good 
results when they are weak or combust and are posited in 
dussthanas. 
GAJA KESARI YOGA: Most modern books on Jyotish inaccurately 
define Gaja Kesari Yoga ('the Elephant-Lion Yoga') as Jupiter in 
the first, fourth, seventh or tenth house (the kendra houses) from the 
Moon. 
Brihat Parashara Hora has a more accurate definition: 
Should Jupiter be in an angle from the ascendant or from the Moon, and be 
conjoined with or aspected by benefics without being debilitated, combust, 
or in an enemy's sign, Gaja Kesari Yoga is formed. One born in Gaja 
Kesari Yoga will be splendorous, wealthy, intelligent, endowed with many 
laudable virtues, and will please the king. (j6:j-4) 
The lesser combination of Moon and Jupiter in angles to each other is 
in Phaladipika given the simpler name of Kesari Yoga, but even in 
this watered-down version of the yoga it is still important for 
Jupiter and the Moon to be in good houses from the ascendant. 
Since one full third of all horoscopes display Jupiter in a kendra 
from the Moon, it is wise to ensure that the combination satisfies 
Parashara's more stringent criteria before predicting the results 
promised for the yoga. A Moon in the twelfth house and a debili- 
tated and combust Jupiter in the third house would clearly be very 
unlikely to produce noticeably good results. 
In Chart I the Moon is in the fifth house and Jupiter in the 
second house, but, although this Jupiter is in an angle from the 
Moon and is exalted, it is also combust and conjoined with Rahu. In 
this case no Gaja Kesari Yoga is formed. A Gaja Kesari Yoga, even 
if in good houses from the ascendant, is also unlikely to yield 
beneficial effects if the Moon is depleted (i.e. if the birth was within 
five days either side of the new Moon). A good Gaja Kesari Yoga is 
said to be particularly useful for politicians. 
This yoga appears almost fully formed in Chart 2, and was the 
cause of the following true story. On a business trip to Bombay, the 
owner of this horoscope was approached on the streets by a strange 
sadbu (a wandering Hindu holy man), who announced with great 
force that our man (let us call him K) must have a Gaja Kesari 


================================================================================
PAGE 317
================================================================================
294 LIGHT ON LIFE 
Yoga in his chart. Knowing his own chart well, K was naturally 
amazed to hear this, and asked the sadhu how he could possibly 
know. The sadhu replied that K's strongly formed, round, vividly 
lustrous forehead indicated a powerful Gaja Kesari Yoga, and then 
forcefully suggested to K that this yoga would permit him to walk 
unharmed among poisonous cobras. The sadhu compellingly invited 
K to accompany him to a live cobra pit to prove the yoga's power, 
but I< adroitly extricated himself from this trial by serpent. There- 
fore we do not yet possess the practical evidence we need to add to 
our list of indications of a strong Gaja Kesari Yoga: '. . . will be 
able to walk amongst poisonous cobras without harm'. It provides, 
however, strong evidence of a good jyotishi's ability to cast a 
horoscope simply by studying a face. 
K E M A D R u M A YOGA : When there is no planet (excluding the Sun) conjoining 
the Moon and no planet in the second or twelfth houses from the Moon and 
no planet (including the Moon) in a kendra from the ascendant. Kemadruma 
Yoga causes the native, even if well-born, to 'be obscure, miserable, 
penurious and menial', and 'be greatly reproached, be bereft of 
intelligence and learning, and be reduced to penury and perils'. 
Some say that Kemadruma is even canceled if any planet occupies a 
kendra as counted from the Moon. 
LA K s H M r YOGA : When the lord of the ninth house and Venus occupy their 
own or exalted constellations in the angular or trine houses. Lakshmi Yoga 
bestows great wealth. Slight variants on this definition can be 
allowed; note that in Chart 2 Venus happens to be the lord of the 
ninth house and occupies its own rashi. It does sit in the second 
house, but since the second house from the ascendant happens to be 
the fifth house, like the ninth a trinal house, from the Moon, we can 
say that Lakshmi Yoga is also present in this horoscope. Yogas 
have both a literal dimension and interpretation and a broadly 
indicative function; and in a horoscope like Chart 2, in which 
beneficial yogas abound, such variations are worthy of 
consideration. 
MA H A B H AGY A YOGA: For a female, birth at night when the Sun, Moon, 
and Lagna all occnpy even rashis; for a male, the reverse (i.e. a da_y birth, 


================================================================================
PAGE 318
================================================================================
GRAHA YOGAS 295 
when the Sun, Moon and Lagna all occupy odd rashis). Maha BhaQa 
means 'exceedingly auspicious'. 
NEEXHA BHANGA RAJA YOGA: Certain planetary combinations can 
modify the detrimental effects of a graha's debilitation. Canceled 
debility does not become equal to an exaltation or some other 
desirable placement, however. Debility is debility, and Neecha 
Bhanga is no more perfect than is a prosthesis applied to a limbless 
body. Giving a debilitated graha a cane with which to walk will 
enable the graha to exert some beneficial effects but, even if it 
excels at its duties, it will still never be normal. Moreover, Neecha 
Bhanga creates a Raja Yoga on4 when the debilitated graha occupies 
a kendra or a kona; otherwise the planet's debility will merely be 
removed. 
Four of the most important ways in which debility can be 
canceled are: (I) if the lord of the rashi occupied by the debilitated 
graha is in a kendra position from the Moon or Lagna; (2) if the 
lord of the rashi where the debilitated graha is exalted is in a kendra 
position from the Moon or Lagna; (3) if the lord of the rashi 
occupied by the debilitated graha aspects that graha; or (4) if the 
planet who would be exalted in the rashi occupied by the debilitated 
graha is in a kendra from the Moon or from the Lagna. 
As an example, take Saturn in Aries. If Mars (I - Saturn's 
dispositor), Venus (2 - lord of Saturn's exaltation rashi) or the Sun 
(4 - who is exalted in Aries) occupies a kendra from the Moon or 
from the Lagna, or if Mars aspects Aries (j), Saturn's debility will 
be canceled. In most of the combinations which redeem a debilitated 
planet, its dispositor must be well placed in some way; the better 
the dispositor biva) is placed, the greater the relief to the debilitated 
planet (deha). The results produced by a debilitated planet will be 
the worst possible when its dispositor is itself debilitated, as would 
happen when, for example, Saturn occupies Aries and its dispositor 
Mars occupies Cancer. 
PA R I VA RTAN A YOGA : When two grahas mutual& occupy each other's 
rashis. lJarivartana Yoga (parivartana means 'exchange' or 'barter'), 
which is also known as 'mutual reception' or 'exchange of houses', 
exists when, for instance, Mars is in Gemini and Mercury in Aries. 


================================================================================
PAGE 319
================================================================================
An exchange between the lords of the kendra houses and of the 
kona houses is deemed to be very beneficial, as is the exchange 
between the lords of dussthanas. The latter exchange typically 
delivers its good effects only after first producing some stressful 
events; for example, some people become famous only after, and 
often because of, first being falsely accused and then extricating 
themselves from the calumny. Or, when you benefit from an 
inheritance, someone (probably a near and dear one) had to die in 
order to leave the bequest. The exchange between the lords of 
other houses usually produces mixed results, some good and some 
bad. 
Parivartana Yoga can also produce evil effects. Here is one case: 
When the lord of the first house occupies the sixth house and the 
sixth lord sits in the lagna, and the lord of the sixth is conjoined 
with or aspected by the lord of a maraka house, the result will be 
penury (Brihat Parashara Hora 42: 3). 
PARVATA YOGA: A Parvata Yoga makes a person wealthy, charit- 
able, eloquent, learned in classical subjects, fond of mirth, famous, 
splendiferous, and the leader of a city. Two of this yoga's several 
definitions appear in Brihat Parashara Hora and in Phaladipika. 
Parashara defines Parvata Yoga as benefics in kendra houses with the 
seventh and eighth houses empty or occupied only by benejcs. Because the 
seventh house is a maraka house, and the eighth house is the worst 
of the trik houses, any planets in those houses should be benefics in 
order to modify their results. Whenever a malefic occupies the 
seventh, it will damage the first house, while a malefic in the eighth 
house will create immense suffering and reduce the lifespan. A 
benefic in the eighth house will at least modify the negative effects 
of the eighth house, though much of the benefit promised by that 
benefic will be lost. To learn yogas thus, by analyzing their likely 
effects instead of merely committing them to memory, is to see how 
Jyotish's basic principles apply to real-life situations. 
Phaladipika states that Parvata Yoga is formed when the dispositor of 
the lord of the ascendant occqies its own rashi while simdtaneotrsly occupying 
a kendra or a kana holrsefrom the l'agna. This writer assumes, but does 
not mention, that the lord of the lagna should also occupy a good 


================================================================================
PAGE 320
================================================================================
position in the horoscope for this yoga to be formed. If the lord of 
the first house is in, say, the eighth house, there will no doubt be 
great benefit to it if its dispositor is in its own rashi in a kendra or 
kona from the lagna, but the benefit will be more along the lines of 
a Neecha Bhanga Raja Yoga, i.e. a cancellation of a miserable 
position. 
PU s H K AL A YOGA: When the Moon's dispositor conjoins the lord of the 
lagna, in a kendra, in a rashi in which it is strong, while at the same time a 
strong benefic aspects the lagna. Those with Pushkala ('plenteous, 
abundant') Yoga, which is a fine example of the importance of the 
dispositor, are wealthy, honored by kings, famous, and beautifully 
adorned. In this case the crucial factor is the dispositor of the 
Moon, since the Moon is second only to the lagna in importance in 
the horoscope. 
s A R A s w AT I YOGA : When Venus, Jupiter and Mercur_y occupy a kendra, a 
kona, or the second home, and all three grahas (Jupiter in particular) are 
strong. This gives skill as a writer, orator or savant. The second 
house is included here because it indicates both speech and classical 
learning. 
s HA KATA YOGA: When the .Moon is in the sixth, eighth or twelfth house 
from Jupiter. The fortunes of those born with this yoga rise and fall 
again and again throughout life, just as a cartwheel (shakata means 
'cart') turns round and round as it rolls down the road. When the 
Moon is in a kendra from the lagna, Shakata Yoga is not formed. 
SHUBHA OR PAPA KARTARI YOGA: When planets sit simultaneously on 
both sides of the first house (i.e. in houses two and twelve). Kartari means 
'scissors'. Shzibba Kartari Yoga occurs when benefics unafflicted by 
malefics flank the first house; when malefics unaspected by benefics 
sit on both sides of the ascendant, the combination is known as 
Papa Kartari Yoga. The former combination is said to be highly 
auspicious (shubha means 'auspicious') and to bestow protection on 
the native by snipping away potential problems. The latter yoga is 
very inauspicious (papa means 'sin') and implies a lack of protection, 
particularly for the matters ruled by the first house, because the 
scissors that the planets form truncate the native's blessings. 


================================================================================
PAGE 321
================================================================================
SUNAPHA, ANAPHA AND DURUDHARA YOGAS: These three combi- 
nations are called lunar yogas because they involve positions counted 
from the Moon alone. When there is a planet other than the Sun, 
Rahu or Ketu in the second house from the Moon, it forms Sunapha 
Yoga; when the same situation exists in the twelfth house counted 
from the Moon, it is Anapha Yoga; and when the prescribed 
combination exists in both the second and twelfth houses from the 
Moon, it becomes Durudhara Yoga. Planets on either side of the 
Moon or (as for Veshi, Voshi and Ubhgyachari Yogas, below) the Sun 
act as heralds for the luminaries, who are the regents of the skies. 
Any planet so near the Moon will be very obvious at night, 
enhancing thereby the Moon's splendor. 
The texts list many meanings for these yogas, but our Jyotish guru 
taught us always to examine the nature of the grahas involved and the 
houses involved in them before even trying to predict their effects. 
Suppose that, for a Libra lagna, the Moon occupies the tenth house in 
Cancer and Mercury sits in the ninth house (the twelfth from the Moon) 
in Gemini. The Anapha Yoga thus created is substantially strengthened 
by the Bhadra Yoga which Mercury creates in the auspicious ninth 
house. We may safely assert that such a yoga will promote writing, 
publishing, higher studies or advanced research, for these are mean- 
ings common to both Mercury and the ninth house. If, for the same 
lagna, Moon tenants Aries in the seventh house and a debilitated 
Mercury forms Anapha Yoga in the sixth house in Pisces, the yoga 
will be hardly worth considering, although theoretically it is better 
for this enfeebled Anapha Yoga to exist than it is for Mercury 
simply to sit debilitated in the sixth house as lord of the ninth house 
of higher studies. 
v A s u M AT YOGA : When the benefc planets all occupy the upachgya houses 
(three, six, ten and eleven) from the Moon or from the Lagna. Vasumat 
means 'rich'. This combination exists in Chart I when counted from 
the Moon, but the planets involved are weak: Jupiter is combust, 
conjoined with and aspected by malefics; Mercury becomes malefic 
because of Saturn's aspect; and Venus is situated in an enemy's 
rashi. 
VESHI, VOSHI AND UBHAYACHARI YOGAS: These solar yogas are 


================================================================================
PAGE 322
================================================================================
GRAHA YOGAS 299 
so called because they involve positions counted exclusively from 
the Sun. If planets other than the Moon, Rahu or Ketu are in the 
second house counted from the Sun, it forms Veshi Yoga; the same 
situation in the twelfth house from the Sun is Voshi Yoga; and such 
a combination in the second and twelfth houses from the Sun is 
Ubhayachari Yoga. Because any planet so near the Sun will appear 
dramatically in the sky either just before sunrise or just after sunset, 
these yogas enhance the Sun's splendor. If the planets involved in 
an Ubha~achari Yoga are exclusively benefics or exclusively malefics, 
the yoga is known as Shubha Ubhayachari Yoga or Papa Ubhayachari 
Yoga respectively. The comments made above for Sunapha, Anapha 
and Durudhara Yogas also apply here. Note that mixed Ubhayachari 
Yogas exist in both Chart I and Chart 2. 
VIPARITA RAJA YOGA: If the lords of at least two dussthanas 
occupy other dussthanas without necessarily exchanging houses 
(which would be a case of ~arivartana Yoga), a Viparita Raja Yoga 
is formed, which tends to cause a sudden and unexpected rise in 
life, often as the result of some mishap (viparita means 'inverted, 
contrary, reversed'). 
THE TWENTY-FOUR YOGAS 
The twenty-four yogas given below are extremely helpful for those 
jyotishis who seek to fuse many factors when making astrological 
judgments. These yogas are specific to each of the twelve houses, 
and their results affect predominantly the matters indicated by the 
relevant house. Twelve of these yogas are auspicious in nature, 
developing the matters indicated by the relevant houses, and twelve 
are inauspicious, obstructing those matters in one way or another. 
The twelve auspicious yogas come about when: 
a house is occupied or aspected by benefics and 
its lord is in a kendra, or a kona, or exalted, or in its own rashi, or 
in a friend's rashi, or is associated with or aspected by benefics 
and 
it is not afflicted by malefics. 


================================================================================
ADDITIONAL REFERENCE - THE ART AND SCIENCE OF VEDIC ASTROLOGY
================================================================================

================================================================================
PAGE 126
================================================================================
CHAPTER TWELVE
THE VIMSHOTARI DASHA SYSTEM
ôThen the Lord said, ôMy spirit shall not abide in man forever, for he is flesh,
but his days shall be a hundred and twenty years.ö 
û Genesis 6:3
ôO Brahmin! The full span of life for a human in Kali Yuga is said to be 120
years. Therefore, amongst the various Dasha systems Vimshotari Dasha is the
prime dasha system.ö
û Brihat-Parashara-Hora-Shastra 46:15
There exist a variety of methods that enable the Jyotishi to understand how
the birth chart unfolds its promise and potential during a personÆs life. The
most widely used method is the 
Vimshotari Dasha
 system, also known as
Udu Dasha
. Sage Parashara, the great authority on Vedic astrology describes
a variety of dasha systems (over 30) in his classic ôBrihat-Parashara-Hora-
Shastra,ö yet gives the greatest attention to expounding the 
Vimshotari
system.
Maitreya said: ôO supreme sage! You are omniscient and have infinite
knowledge. Kindly be merciful and enlighten me in detail about the planetary
dashas.ö
Maharishi Parashara said: ôO Brahmin! You have asked a most
appropriate question which will benefit one and all. I now unfold the secrets
of the prevailing dasha systems. There are various types of dasha in use but
for ordinary people Vimshotari dasha is the predominant one.ö 
û Brihat-
Parashara- Hora-Shastra 46:1-3
Vimshotari
 means 120 and 
Dasha
 means a stage, condition, or period of life.
Thus this 
dasha
 system covers a period of 120 years of life. 
Vimshotari
Dasha
 is composed of 9 planetary periods or cycles 
(dashas)
 which vary
between 6 and 20 years each.


================================================================================
PAGE 127
================================================================================
Although always occurring in this order the exact starting point will be
determined by the zodiacal position of the Moon at birth which, although
described in terms of degrees and minutes of a sign, will always correspond
to one of the Lunar 
Nakshatras
.
Planet
Span of
Years
Ketu
7
Venus
20
Sun
6
Moon
10
Mars
7
Rahu
18
Jupiter
16
Saturn
19
Mercury
17
Total
120
Nakshatra
 means a constellation or small group of stars. These are found by
dividing the ecliptic into 27 equal segments of 13░20Æ, beginning 0░ Aries.
The following list gives the number and name of each 
Nakshatra
, followed
by the area of the zodiac to which it corresponds and the planet which rules
that particular 
Nakshatra
.
Notice that the planets ruling the 
Nakshatras
 repeat their sequence three
times. Thus each planet rules three 
Nakshatras
. No one can convincingly
explain just why the planets are arranged in this sequence or rule the number
of years that they do. It remains an occult mystery.
The time span covered by each of the nine planets is known as its
mahadasha
. Each 
mahadasha
 is subdivided into nine subperiods or sub-
cycles known as 
bhuktis
. If the birth time was correctly recorded and
accurately known then even the 
bhuktis
 can each be subdivided into nine
smaller time periods known as 
antardashas
. Thus the 
mahadasha
 of the Sun
is composed of nine 
bhuktis
, The first 
bhukti
 would be of the Sun itself, the
second would be that of the Moon, the third would be of Mars, and so onù
always following the same order as the 
mahadasha
 planets. The same


================================================================================
PAGE 128
================================================================================
sequence also applies to the 
antardashas
.
1
Ashwini
0░- 13░20Æ Aries
Ketu 7 years
2
Bharani
13░20Æ - 26░40Æ Aries
Venus 20 years
3
Krittika
26░40Æ Aries - 10░ Taurus
Sun 6 years
4
Rohini
10░ - 23░20Æ Taurus
Moon 10 years
5
Mrigashira
23░20Æ Taurus - 6░40ÆGemini
Mars 7 years
6
Ardra
6░40Æ - 20░ Gemini
Rahu 18 years
7
Punarvasu
20░ Gemini - 3░20Æ Cancer
Jupiter 16 years
8
Pushya
3░20Æ - 16░40Æ Cancer
Saturn 19 years
9
Ashlesha
16░40Æ - 30░ Cancer
Mercury 17 years
10
Magha
0░- 13░20Æ Leo
Ketu 7 years
11
Purva-Phalguni
13░20Æ - 26░40Æ Leo
Venus 20 years
12
Uttara-Phalguni
26░40Æ Leo - 10░ Virgo
Sun 6 years
13
Hasta
10░ - 23░20Æ Virgo
Moon 10 years
14
Chitra
23░20Æ Virgo - 6░40Æ Libra
Mars 7 years
15
Swati
6░40Æ - 20░ Libra
Rahu 18 years
16
Vishakha
20░ Libra - 3░20Æ Scorpio
Jupiter 16 years
17
Anuradha
3░20Æ -16░40Æ Scorpio
Saturn 19 years
18
Jyeshta
16░40Æ - 30░ Scorpio
Mercury 17 years
19
Mula
0░ - 13░20Æ Sagittarius
Ketu 7 years
20
Purvashadha
13░20Æ - 26░40Æ Sagittarius
Venus 20 years
21
Uttarashadha
26░40Æ Sagittarius -10░ Capricorn
Sun 6 years
22
Shravana
10░ - 23░20Æ Capricorn
Moon 10 years
23
Dhanishta
23░20Æ Capricorn - 6░40ÆAquarius
Mars 7 years
24
Shatabhishak
6░40Æ - 20░ Aquarius
Rahu 18 years
25
Purvabhadra
20░ Aquarius - 3░20Æ Pisces
Jupiter 16 years
26
Uttarabhadra
3░20Æ - 16░40Æ Pisces
Saturn 19 years
27
Revati
16░40Æ - 30░ Pisces
Mercury 17 years
In order to arrive at the 
mahadasha
 (period) and 
bhukti
 (sub-periods)
operating at the time of birth you will need to make some calculations.


================================================================================
PAGE 129
================================================================================
Details of how the necessary calculations are made in order to establish the
dasha
 balance at birth are given at the end of this section.
From here on we shall follow the common practice of referring to a
mahadasha
 as a 
dasha
. Also note, in some areas of India the 
bhuktis
 (sub-
periods) are referred to as 
antardashas
 and the 
antardashas
 (sub- sub-
periods) as 
pratyantar-dashas
 These differences of terminology should be
born in mind when reading books on jyotish.
How to Calculate the Dashas
Although these days most astrologers use a computer program to make these
calculations it is still useful to know how they are constructed and the method
of making these calculations on paper. Many Indian Ephemerids and some
books on Jyotish give tables for speedy calculation of dasha and bhuktis.
Here we give an illustration of how the dashas are arrived at, taking as an
example the dashas and bhuktis of John LennonÆs chart.
First we take the position of the Moon at birth, which in John LennonÆs
case is 4░30Æ of Capricorn. By referring to the Nakshatra table at the
beginning of this section you will find that the Moon is placed in the
Nakshatra of Uttarashada which is ruled by the Sun. Therefore the dasha
period at birth will be that of the Sun. If he had been born at the very
beginning of Uttarashada (26░40Æ of Sagittarius) he would have the full 6
years of the Sun dasha to run. As this was not the case we have to calculate
the exact point of the dasha into which he was born and determine how long
it continued before changing to the next dasha.
To do this, we have first to convert the proper length of the Naksha- tra
(always 13░20Æ) into minutes of space. As 60 = 1░, 13░20Æ = 800Æ.
Next we calculate the distance covered by the Moon in this particular
Nakshatra. Uttarashada begins at 26░40Æ Sagittarius and ends a 10░
Capricorn. As the Moon is placed in 4░30 minutes of Capricorn we know that
the Moon has covered a distance of 7░50Æ in Uttarashada (3░20Æ of Sag. +
4░30Æ of Capricorn = 7░50Æ). This leaves another 5░30Æ of Uttarashad
remaining to be traversed by the Moon. Converting 5░30Æ to minutes of space
we find that the Moon has still to travel 330Æ of Uttarashada. At this point
using a calculator will be helpful.
Divide the remaining distance by 800. 330 divided by 800 = 0.4125


================================================================================
PAGE 130
================================================================================
which is the percentage of the period which remains between the Moon and
the end of the Nakshatra. As the Sun dasha lasts for 6 years we multiply
0.4125 by 6. The result is 2.475 or 2 years and .475 months. Multiply .475 by
12 to get the months (.475 x 12 = 5.7). Multiply .7 by 30 to get the days (.7 x
30 = 21). Therefore 2 years 5 months and 21 days of the Sun dasha remains.
The date of John LennonÆs birth was 9
th
 October 1940 and the Moon in
Uttarashada is ruled by the Sun. After 2 years 5 months and 21 days (1
st
 April
1943) his Sun dasha ended and his Moon dasha begun. As the Moon dasha
lasts exactly 10 years it ended on 1
st
 April 1953 and the Mars dasha began.
As the Mars dasha runs for 7 years, on the 1
st
 April 1960 his Rahu dasha
commenced.
Calculating the Bhuktis (Sub-periods)
The nine bhuktis of the main dasha period appear in the same order as the
mahadashas. The first bhukti planet is always the same as the main dasha
planet. Thus Rahu dasha always begins with Rahu bhukti, followed by Jupiter
bhukti, then Saturn bhukti and so on. The lengths of the bhuktis are
proportionate in length to the main dashas, as are the 
antardashas
.
With the tabulation of the dasha and bhukti periods that follows it is a
simple matter of counting back from the end of the first (birth) dasha in order
to calculate the bhukti that was running at the time of birth and the number of
days and months that had to elapse before the next one commenced.
Tables of Planetary Periods
Guidelines for Judging the Dashas
So how do we make use of the dashas and bhuktis?
ôWhatever has been described here by way of planetary effects will occur in
the planetÆs [maha]dasha, in its bhukti and in its antar[dasha].ö
û Phaldeepika 21:1
Ketu Mahadasha û 7 years


================================================================================
PAGE 131
================================================================================
Bhukti planet
Year
Month
Day
Ketu
0
4
27
Venus
1
2
0
Sun
0
4
6
Moon
0
7
0
Mars
0
4
27
Rahu
1
0
18
Jupiter
0
11
16
Saturn
1
1
9
Mercury
0
11
27
Venus Mahadasha û 20 years
Bhukti
Planet
Year
Month
Day
Venus
3
4
0
Sun
1
0
0
Moon
1
8
0
Mars
1
2
0
Rahu
3
0
0
Jupiter
2
8
0
Saturn
3
2
0
Mercury
2
10
0
Ketu
1
2
0
Sun Mahadasha û 6 years
Bhukti
Planet
Year
Month
Day
Sun
0
3
18
Moon
0
6
0
Mars
0
4
6
Rahu
0
10
24
Jupiter
0
9
18


================================================================================
PAGE 132
================================================================================
Saturn
0
11
12
Mercury
0
10
6
Ketu
0
4
6
Venus
1
0
0
Moon Mahadasha û 10 years
Bhukti
Planet
Year
Month
Day
Moon
0
10
0
Mars
0
7
0
Rahu
1
6
0
Jupiter
1
4
0
Saturn
1
7
0
Mercury
1
5
0
Ketu
0
7
0
Venus
1
8
0
Sun
0
6
0
Mars Mahadasha û 7 years
Bhukti
Planet
Year
Month
Day
Mars
0
4
27
Rahu
1
0
18
Jupiter
0
11
6
Saturn
1
1
9
Mercury
0
11
27
Ketu
0
4
27
Venus
1
2
0
Sun
0
4
6
Moon
0
7
0
Rahu Mahadasha û 18 years


================================================================================
PAGE 133
================================================================================
Bhukti
Planet
Year
Month
Day
Rahu
2
8
12
Jupiter
2
4
24
Saturn
2
10
6
Mercury
2
6
18
Ketu
1
0
18
Venus
3
0
0
Sun
0
10
24
Moon
1
6
0
Mars
1
0
18
Jupiter Mahadasha û 16 years
Bhukti
Planet
Year
Month
Day
Jupiter
2
1
18
Saturn
2
6
12
Mercury
2
3
6
Ketu
0
11
6
Venus
2
8
0
Sun
0
9
18
Moon
1
4
0
Mars
0
11
6
Rahu
2
4
24
Saturn Mahadasha û 19 years
Bhukti
Planet
Year
Month
Day
Saturn
3
0
3
Mercury
2
8
9
Ketu
1
1
9
Venus
3
2
0
Sun
0
11
12


================================================================================
PAGE 134
================================================================================
Moon
1
7
0
Mars
1
1
9
Rahu
2
10
6
Jupiter
2
6
12
Mercury Mahadasha û 17 years
Bhukti
Planet
Year
Month
Day
Mercury
2
4
27
Ketu
0
11
27
Venus
2
10
0
Sun
0
10
6
Moon
1
5
0
Mars
0
11
27
Rahu
2
6
18
Jupiter
2
3
6
Saturn
2
8
9
The ability to accurately judge the development and outcome of someoneÆs
horoscope based on the dashas and bhuktis operating at any particular time is
a skill that is acquired gradually and as a result of careful study and analysis.
The following essential guidelines should help you in acquiring the
ability to judge the periods and subperiods with a fair degree of accuracy.
Final conclusions should be arrived at only after comparing the dasha
indications with the appropriate planetary transits.
Analyze the dasha results based upon the following:
Lordship
: A dasha lord gives results according to houses over which it has
lordship.
Position
: A dasha lord will give results pertaining to the house in which it is
placed.
Aspect and Conjunction
: A dasha lord will give results modified by the
nature of any planet that aspects or conjuncts it.


================================================================================
PAGE 135
================================================================================
Dasha Results according to Planetary Strength
If a planet is strong and well placed by sign it gives well-being and
abundance in accordance with its nature.
If a planet is weak (by house and sign) it contributes to poor health and
lack of prosperity.
If proceeding towards its point of debilitation 
(avarohi)
 its dasha
inclines towards trouble and difficulty.
If proceeding towards its point of exaltation 
(aarohi)
 its dasha inclines
to be more auspicious.
If a planet is well placed in the divisional charts (particularly the
navamsha) its dasha proves even more beneficial.
During the dasha of a planet possessing directional strength (Jupiter and
Mercury posses directional strength in the 1
st
 house, Venus and the Moon in
the 4
th
 house, Saturn in the 7
th
 and Sun and Mars in the 10
th
) the person will
be successful in their ventures and will benefit from the direction indicated by
the planet.
Dasha Results According to Planetary Position
Any planet placed in a kendra (1
st
,4
th
, 7
th
 or 10
th
) or kona (5
th
 or 9
th
)
will prove fruitful.
Any planet occupying the 6
th
, 8
th
 or 12
th
 house will tend to be harmful
or troublesome. The dasha of a lord of the 6
th
, 8
th
 or 12
th
 house becomes
beneficial if it is associated with a kona lord.
The dasha of a natural benefic will fail to give good results if it is in the
3
rd
, 6
th
 or 11
th
 house. However, the dasha of a natural malefic, if placed
in these houses, will prove helpful in that it will not manifest malefic
results.
The most benefic dasha is that of the lord of (a) kendra in a kona or
associated with a kona lord, or (b) a kona lord placed in a kendra or
associated with a kendra lord.
The dashas of planets (a) posited in the 2
nd
 or 7
th
 houses (maraca
houses), (b) associated with 2
nd
 or 7
th
 lords, or (c) placed in the 8
th


================================================================================
PAGE 136
================================================================================
house, can indicate health problems or, if occurring at an appropriate
time, indicate death.
Other Principal Considerations
The prime rule is to remember that whatever a planet indicates in the
birthchart will be emphasized and highlighted during the planetÆs dasha.
The dasha of a debilitated lord of the 3
rd
, 6
th
, or 8
th
 house, or the dasha of
a debilitated planet posited in the 3
rd
, 6
th
, or 8
th
 house, does not have the
power to bring about the negative qualities associated with these houses.
During a planetÆs dasha all those things for which it is a karaka
(representative) will become activated.
Any yogas in which the planet participates will become emphasized.
When a planet owns two houses, the house that contains its Moolatrikona
sign will predominate. The effects of the other house will be less emphasized.
Even so, matters associated with both houses will come to pass during the
dasha period of the planet.
The house the planet owns that is first in sign sequence will tend to give its
results during the first half of the dasha and the remaining house during the
second half of the dasha. For example if someone has a chart with a Scorpio
Ascendant, Saturn will rule the 3
rd
 (Capricorn) and 4
th
 (Aquarius) house.
During the dasha of Saturn the first nine or so years would manifest matters
more associated with 3
rd
 house matters and the remaining years would be
more associated with 4
th
 house affairs. As the 4
th
 house contains the
moolatrikona sign the second half of the dasha will be much more significant
and eventful.
The house occupied by the dasha lordÆs dispositorùthe planet which
owns the sign in which the dasha lord is placedùas well as the affairs of
houses aspected by the dispositor, will also become activated.
No planet is entirely good or bad in its effects. Consider the natural
tendencies of the planet as well as the qualities that it acquires due to house
ownership of the chart under consideration.
Is the dasha lord in exaltation, own sign, friendly, neutral or enemy sign,
or in its sign of fall? These factors will also have a decided influence on the
manner in which it functions.

